Hi everyone. Well, sorry I can't be
there in person.
Um, I thought I would talk about a few
things that I think might be relevant to
machine consciousness.
Uh, we'll see. So, I'm going to start
with some things that uh uh
from a long time ago and I'm going to
end with some things that I just made
about 15 minutes ago. So, we'll see
we'll see what happens with that.
So,
long time ago I got interested in the
question of kind of how come we
understand things in the natural world,
complicated things and so on. What's
what's This is sort of the goal of
theoretical science is to be able to
understand the natural world. I mean,
>> Recording in progress.
>> the the role of science in general to be
um
uh
to to sort of find a bridge between what
actually happens in the world and the
kinds of things that we can fit as
narratives in our minds. That's kind of
the the the the role that science plays
is to make that bridge.
So, the question is sort of what's the
right raw material to use for for that
bridge. And the thing that I got to
thinking at the beginning of the 1980s
now is uh let's generalize from the
kinds of things that we get in
mathematics. Let's uh use arbitrary
kinds of rules to describe what might be
happening in the natural world. And so,
that got me into the whole business of
thinking about sort of the computational
universe and what's out there in the
computational universe. Let me see if I
can show you some things.
So, um
uh
started kind of
pointing sort of a computational
telescope out into the computational
universe see what's out there.
You can uh start with very simple kinds
of rules like the one at the bottom
here. This is a typical cellular
automaton rule um where you have the
simple rule for what the color of each
successive cell will be. You start off
with one black cell, you end up just
with um
uh a simple a simple pattern there.
So, the question then is, well,
what what happens if we think about this
process of going from rules
to their consequences,
we can think of that. In modern times,
the best metaphor we have for that is
computation, but the basic idea is we've
defined some rules, now we want to run
those rules and see their consequences.
And so, the one very basic question that
one can ask is, if one just looks at
lots of typical simple rules, what kinds
of behavior does one see?
And so, uh it's an experiment I did a
really long time ago, is just look at
all possible rules of the kind that I
just showed you, and see what kinds of
things happen.
Well, actually,
uh
it will be um
42 years ago
on Monday that I saw this thing. That's
um kind of to me the most sort of
surprising and remarkable science
discovery I've ever been able to make,
and it's sort of led us over the course
of many years
not quite to the answer to life, the
universe, and everything, but uh at 42
years, we're we're getting a lot closer,
and I want to talk a bit about that
today.
What's surprising about this? What's
surprising is that even though the rule
by which this picture is generated is
that simple thing at the bottom of the
page, the picture once generated is
something very complicated. It's a thing
it's sort of a remarkable phenomenon
that even though one can have very
simple rules, the behavior one gets is
very complicated. That's uh
uh that's sort of a a key discovery that
will lead to everything I'm going to
talk about, and will lead to thinking
about what minds are like, what the
universe is like, and so on.
So, this turns out to be a very generic
thing in the world of simple programs.
It's not something that we have been
very familiar with because the the kinds
of things that we set up for
engineering, for technology, and so on
tend to be things where we can kind of
readily foresee what the consequences of
the things we build are. And so, we
don't end up building things where we
just set up rules and then let those
rules run and see what happens. It's
kind of we I think we've lived in a kind
of a unique 100-year period since the
Industrial Revolution of a time when one
can expect to understand the devices
one's making. I mean, one one's using.
You know, before that time you would
like ride a horse. You could know how to
control the horse a bit. You wouldn't
know how the horse you wouldn't expect
to know how sort of the horse works
inside. But then, sort of with the
Industrial Revolution, we got to the
point where there are cogs and levers
and so on where you can kind of look
inside the machine and see what happens.
Well, in the computational universe of
possible programs, most programs in the
end won't have that characteristic.
They'll be more like this Rule 30 uh
program here where you can set up the
rules. The rules are very simple, but
the behavior you get can be very
complicated. That's the generic thing
that you see in the computational
universe.
This has many consequences. So, one
question you might ask is, "Okay,
uh given how how much can we predict
given the rules what a system will do?"
That's kind of been the conceit of
traditional theoretical science. It's
all about kind of reductionism and
getting down to those sort of simple
rules, simple rules that describe a
system. And the idea is once you found
those simple rules, then you can
immediately deduce everything about what
the system will do. That's been the
thing that sort of worked in
mathematical science in the late 1600s
and so on for things like celestial
mechanics. And the question is, "How
general is that phenomenon?" How general
is it that you can go from sort of the
underlying laws, the underlying rules
for a system to figure out the behavior
of that system?
Well, one of the surprises is that kind
of in the computational universe,
it is not the case that you can readily
go from those underlying laws
immediately to the consequences of what
happens. Instead, you can certainly find
out what will happen by just using the
rule and and going step by step and
seeing what the consequences of the rule
will be. But, you won't in general be
able to kind of jump ahead and
immediately say, "Given the rule, I know
what's going to happen."
So, I call this phenomenon computational
irreducibility. The idea that to know
what will happen, you have to kind of
follow each step and see what happens.
It's something which I think has sort of
fundamental consequences for for lots
and lots of things, but but two that
I'll mention, one of them has to do with
kind of the the dichotomy between things
like free will and determinism.
The picture we're seeing here is a
picture which is completely
deterministic. Given the underlying
rule, it's inevitable that the bits will
will be the way that they are in this in
this image.
But, so you might say, "Well, that means
that given this underlying rule, it's
completely determined kind of what this
idealized creature in a sense will in
some idealized sense think."
But, the fact is you can't know what
this thing will do except by essentially
running it at each step and seeing what
it does. And I think that's sort of the
essence of how it can be the case that a
system which, even though it has
underlying determinism, can still seem
as if it's free of that underlying
determinism. As if the only way that it
can know what it will do is to do it is
to actually do it itself.
So,
this phenomenon of computational
irreducibility, as I say, lots of
consequences. If you're interested in
things like AIs and trying to get AIs to
do the things that you want them to do
and not the things you don't want them
to do, well, computational
irreducibility kind of has a thing to
say about that. It kind of says that
there's there will always be surprises.
There will always be things where you
can only know what will happen by
explicitly running the system and seeing
what it does.
So, in a sense, if you're building
something like an AI, you kind of have a
choice. You can either say, "Oh, I don't
want it ever to do anything with will be
a surprise."
Okay, you can achieve that by making the
system computationally reducible. Make
it behave in some way that is very
readily predictable. Or you can say,
"Well, actually, I'm I want the system
to do sort of the richest and most
sophisticated things it can." But then
you are inevitably faced with
computational irreducibility, and it's
inevitable that there will be things
that the system can do that will
surprise you.
So, you know, lots of things you can ask
in in terms of of computational
irreducibility. I just made this picture
a few minutes ago just as an example of
something where you could look at the
top of this picture and you could say,
"What's going to happen?"
And you'll say, "Well, I don't really
know."
Well, how can I find out? Well, I can
just run the the rule for this picture
and just see what happens. I think I I
picked out another couple here of them.
Well, you can kind of see examples.
Here's Here's one where it's it kind of
looks um in that top red piece that it's
just going to do something really,
really simple. But then it surprises us
and it keeps surprising us. You know, if
you had your AI set up and you thought
it was going to do just that simple red
thing,
then you would be surprised cuz
something different would happen. And
that's an inevitable feature of
computational irreducibility.
Well, okay. So, given our understanding
that even very simple rules can do very
complicated things. An obvious question
to ask if you want to go big is what
about the whole universe?
Could it be the case that our whole
universe is actually the result of just
running some very simple rule over and
over again and that everything we see in
the universe is a consequence of the
output from that from that rule from
essentially the computation that's done
in the the successive application of
that rule.
So, about six years ago made sort of a
big breakthrough in understanding the
answer to that question and I have to
say I was not expecting this to be
anything like as comparatively easy as
it was, but I think we managed to kind
of figure out what sort of the machine
code of the universe looks like. What
exists underneath space and time and
quantum mechanics and so on. What the
kind of raw material that the universe
is made of is like.
So, there are many different ways that
one can sort of present the answer to
that, but the one that I think is most
accessible so far as I can tell to us
humans is to think about sort of space
and everything in it as consisting of
kind of these discrete elements where
all you know is kind of how those
elements are related to each other.
Back in antiquity, there was a a sort of
big debate about is the universe
fundamentally discrete or fundamentally
continuous?
By the end of the 19th century, that
question had been answered for matter.
One knew that matter was discrete and
made of atoms and molecules and so on.
Beginning of the 20th century, most
people thought that space would turn out
to be discrete as well.
But at the time the kind of mathematical
methods
couldn't really figure that out. A
hundred years later, we have been able
to figure that out and we can say that
we can sort of understand the machine
code of the universe as being something
where sort of everything in the universe
is a feature of the structure of space
and space is something which is made of
discrete elements and where what
describes the structure of space is kind
of the relations between those discrete
elements.
So, a bit like a cellular automaton
where you're just following a rule over
and over again, you can say, "Well, how
would this giant network that represents
space and everything in it, how would it
get built up?"
Well, you could have some very simple
rule, perhaps, that replaces one piece
of a network with another piece of
network. You run that rule for a while
and you'll start getting more and more
complicated structures that
will eventually build up something that
um
uh one can think of as corresponding to
the to the structure of space.
So, for example, I probably got a
picture. Uh
So, that's kind of a a a view of sort of
the the very beginning of the universe
as uh uh
in at the very very lowest level. I
mean, the the picture that we're seeing
and all that wobbling around and so on
is just kind of the bridge to kind of
human understanding of trying to render
what is fundamentally just a set of
connections between sort of the the
fundamental atoms of space.
Well, so one of the big things that I
first kind of sort of figured out in the
1990s, but really became clear only
about 6 years ago, is the question of,
"Well, what happens if you have all
these atoms of space and all these
rewrite rules and so on, what what is
that like when you have immense numbers
of those
atoms of space?"
Well, there's a close analogy to this,
which is what happens if you look at a
fluid like water or something. It
consists of a whole bunch of discrete
molecules bouncing around, but a
surprising fact is that all of those
discrete molecules, when you look at
them on a large scale, seem to
correspond to something that's like a
continuously flowing fluid and that
obeys the equations of fluid dynamics.
Well, if you work out the same kind of
thing for these discrete hypergraphs and
so on, these discrete networks and such
like, then
it turns out that the analog of the sort
of large-scale limit corresponding to a
fluid and fluid dynamics is that the
large-scale limit corresponds to what we
know about space-time and what we know
about things like the Einstein equations
for the structure of space-time.
So, what we're saying is that that we
have sort of this picture of what the
universe is fundamentally made of. It's
fundamentally made of these atoms of
space related by these uh uh
uh with with with these relations
between them.
Well,
it turns out that one of the other
things that happens is sort of the
progress of time in the universe in this
kind of model is a sort of
computationally irreducible process of
the successive rewriting of this network
that represents the structure of space.
So, the passage of time is sort of the
doing of the computation that
corresponds to applying the underlying
rules for this network and for the
universe.
Well, one of the things that happens is
there are these rules that you're
applying to different uh to to this
network saying, "Whenever you see a
little piece of network that looks like
that, replace it by one that looks like
that." and so on.
Well, one of the things about that is
there isn't a unique way to do that. You
could apply one rule here, another rule
there, and so on. You actually build up
kind of a multiway graph of different
possibilities for kind of the
progression of the universe, different
threads of time, different kind of uh
paths of history. And there many places
where this kind of multiway process uh
one
can be seen. So, for example, if you're
if you have sort of an idealized game of
tic-tac-toe, simplified a bit here, you
can say, "Well, what are all the
possible moves you can make in that game
of tic-tac-toe?" Those can be
represented by this multiway graph, and
And can think about each possible game
play for tic-tac-toe as corresponding to
a possible sort of path of history, a
possible thread of history, a possible
kind of progression of time.
So, when you start thinking about this
kind of whole structure of the universe
in terms of this network of that
represents the structure of space, and
then the rewriting of that network with
many paths of history, it turns out that
this picture of many paths of history
that branch and merge and so on, this
turns out to
show one the kind of path to quantum
mechanics. Quantum mechanics, the sort
of essential feature of it is that it
involves many paths of history. When
people thought about things like the
many worlds theory of quantum mechanics,
they kind of missed the point that in a
discrete universe, you don't just have
branching of different possible
histories, you also have merging of
different possible histories, and that's
kind of critical to kind of knitting
together this what we call branchial
space, the space of quantum branches.
So, one of the things that
that then happens is when it comes to
how do we perceive quantum mechanics,
we are kind of somewhere embedded in the
space of all possible quantum branches.
Actually, our minds are branching and
merging just like the universe is
branching and merging. And so, so that
the story of quantum mechanics becomes a
story of kind of how do branching and
merging minds perceive a branching and
merging universe?
And one of the things that sort of
critical is that we believe that we
experience a single thread of history.
So, we're always trying to take
everything that might happen with all
those different threads of history and
sort of compress them down, conflate
them into a single path of history.
And um
if we had kind of quantum brains, then
we would be perfectly well able to deal
with many threads of history
simultaneously. That's what sort of
happens inside a quantum computer. The
challenge for quantum computers, what I
think is in practice rather hard to
achieve, is kind of to knit together
those different kind of paths of quantum
history to get out a definite answer
that brains like ours that experience a
single thread of history find
satisfactory.
Well, okay. So, then the the question
might be okay, we have this um
uh this we have this idea that um we can
generate the laws of physics and so on
from some underlying rule, just applying
that rule over and over again, getting
the structure of space, quantum
mechanics, gravity, all those kinds of
good things.
But the question then that you could ask
is, well, why did our universe get one
particular rule and not another one?
I was very confused about that for quite
a while, but then I realized, just like
in quantum mechanics, one is applying
all these different possible uh applying
these underlying rules in all the
different possible places, so
similarly, one can say, what about
applying all possible rules in all
possible ways?
So, the result of of that process of
applying all possible rules in all
possible ways is what I call the
ruleiad. It's the entangled limit of all
possible computational processes. So,
for example, you could represent it in
terms of let's say Turing machines, just
looking at all possible rules for Turing
machines, applying them, and generating
this whole structure. What gives this
thing sort of interesting structure is
the fact that two different Turing
machines may end up generating the same
state. So, you don't just have kind of
the branching of all possible different
rules, you also have merging of
equivalent rules.
Well, so the kind of the the The that
emerges is the set of all possible
computations, the rule-iad, is kind of
the underlying stuff from which
everything gets made. And so, we talk
about the sort of elements, the data
structure on which the the individual
sort of atoms of of the data structure
on which the rule-iad operates as being
the eems, the the underlying elements
which
in the case of physical space are
interpreted as atoms of space. Uh in in
other cases, they're interpreted in
different ways. But in the end, there's
sort of these these fundamental
indivisible
uh elements whose only feature is that
they have a certain identity and they're
related to other such elements.
But one builds up sort of everything
that is conceivable is this rule-iad
object. And the thing that's kind of
remarkable about it is it's a unique
object. There's just one of it. Once you
have kind of the idea of computational
rules, it then becomes inevitable that
you will be able to build or you could
will build the rule-iad, and it will be
just the rule-iad and nothing but the
rule-iad, so to speak. So, in a sense,
when you ask questions about sort of
why is the universe the way it is? Well,
the only thing that can be is this
rule-iad object. But then the question
is, given that sort of necessary object,
how do we perceive that object? We are
observers somehow embedded within the
rule-iad, and the question then is
about how we perceive the rule-iad, how
observers like us perceive the rule-iad.
And in a sense, what we want to know, if
we want to understand the laws of
physics that we perceive, is how does an
observer like us
perceive what's happening in this
inevitable necessary object that is the
rule-iad?
And this is something that I have to say
I absolutely did not see coming, but I
find it very kind of exciting that But
is how things seem to work.
That it turns out that for observers who
are even roughly like us, it becomes
inevitable that what we must perceive in
the rulead is something that
follows the laws of physics that we
know.
So actually there are there are two
characteristics of observers like us
that I know for sure are important.
One is that we are computationally
bounded.
In other words, there's kind of a limit
to the amount of computation that gets
done in our minds. And so that means for
example that if we're confronted with a
a whole lot of computational
irreducibility, we can't kind of unravel
all that computational irreducibility.
We with our minds can only do
computation at a certain small rate. We
can only do kind of simple computations
with our minds. So the first thing is we
are computationally bounded.
The second thing is we believe we
experience things in a sort of single
thread of experience. We we kind of and
and that that thread of experience is
persistent through time.
That that's a a feature of uh the way
that we that we are.
We are presumably made of different
atoms of space at every successive
moment of time, but nevertheless we have
the belief that we are experiencing
things persistently through time, that
we exist persistently through time.
These two features that of observers
like us, that we're computationally
bounded and that we believe we are
persistent in time and we have this
single thread of experience through
time.
Those two features of observers
turn out to imply that
that such observers observing the rulead
inevitably must perceive, it turns out,
the laws of physics that we know to be
the case.
So that's a that's a very remarkable
thing. It means that it is inevitable
for observers like us that we must
perceive physics the way that physically
perceive physics. In other words, we're
able to derive the laws of physics. The
laws of physics aren't just something
that happens to be given to us by the
universe. The laws of physics are
inevitable for observers like us.
So, there's one case of this that's
somewhat easy to see, which is what
happens with the second law of
thermodynamics. So, the second law of
thermodynamics says if you have some
collection of things, let's say
molecules, and they start off in some
very orderly configuration, chances are
they'll end up looking random after a
while. And you can characterize that by
saying that the entropy, the number of
states of the system consistent with
what you know about it, increases.
Things tend to get more random through
time. That's the kind of what the second
law of thermodynamics says.
Well,
you can kind of reduce things down to,
for example, just a simple cellular
automaton where you start off with some
kind of orderly initial condition, and
the cellular automaton is
microscopically reversible. So, if
you've got any particular state of the
system, you could in principle go
backwards and figure out that it came
from that simple initial state.
But, the point is that if you are a
computationally bounded observer, you
can't do that. A computationally bounded
observer, when confronted with something
that is sort of many steps down in this
evolution, will just have to say, "I
can't tell what's going on. That just
seems random to me."
And so, the the sort of origin of the
second law of thermodynamics is that the
underlying dynamics of molecules and
things like that is computationally
irreducible, but we are computationally
bounded observers, so it inevitably
becomes the case that we can't kind of
untangle, decode that irreducible
evolution of those molecules, and so we
just say that it seems like things are
getting more random. So, the second law
of thermodynamics wouldn't be the way it
is if we were not computationally
bounded observers. If we were able to be
computationally sophisticated enough to
untangle all of that irreducible
computation that's going on, then we
wouldn't believe in the second law of
thermodynamics. We would just say, "We
know that this particular configuration
of molecules came from this very simple
thing." But, it's because we are
computationally bounded that we believe
in the second law of thermodynamics. The
second law of thermodynamics is an
inevitable consequence of our
computational boundedness, given the
kind of inevitability of computational
irreducibility in the underlying
dynamics of the system.
Well, the big surprise is that that same
argument can be used for general
relativity, the theory of space-time,
and quantum mechanics. Both of those, in
fact, sort of all three of the key
theories of 20th century physics turn
out to be, it seems, derivable from the
underlying idea of the ruliad, plus the
fact that we are observers of the kind
we are.
Well,
it's uh it's sort of a question of uh
if if we look at kind of the
the whole
When we think about sort of what are
minds like?
Well, we might say, you know, what's
great about minds is that they can
follow rules and do computations, and
we've got all these neurons in our in
our brains that are firing in all these
patterns that follow certain laws of
physics, and that, like the cellular
automata and other things I've shown
you, even though their rules might be
simple, they can do all kinds of
complicated things.
Well,
the thing to understand is
the universe is full of computation. The
the the whole the whole operation of the
universe we can think of as a
computation, and a question that we
might ask is, what's I
is the computation that's done in our
brains kind of uh something very
sophisticated relative to the rest of
the universe, or is it actually
something very special and and specific
relative to the rest of the universe?
I think it's something very specific. I
think if we look at kind of the universe
as a whole, there's an immense amount of
computation going on in it at all times.
What's special about the computation
that is embodied in our minds and that
we kind of that gives us our perception
of consciousness and so on. I think that
there are a couple of things that are
special. Two very immediate things that
are special are we computationally
bounded and we believe we we experience
things in this single thread of time.
Those are Those Those two features make
us very specific relative to all the
computation that's going on in the
universe. You know, we might say a sort
of an aphorism, you know, the weather
has a mind of its own, but the weather
is is this thing that has all of these
different sort of pockets of of air
flowing around and so on. It's lots of
things doing doing lots of things kind
of separately. The thing that I think is
sort of special about us and the way
that we sort of operate as observers of
the universe is first that we're
computationally bounded and second that
we try and crush things down to the
point where we have this kind of single
thread of experience. I mean, I think my
my sort of picture of what what minds in
our brains do is they take all kinds of
uh of of input, you know, every second
we're getting millions of of bytes of of
input from our eyes and ears and so on,
and our brains go to a lot of trouble to
sort of crush that down to the point
where, you know, 10 times a second or
something, we are deciding to actuate
this muscle or that muscle. It's a It's
a big process of kind of compressing all
of this input that we have down to this
sort of single thread of what we
consider to be our inner experience.
And I think that's sort of the essence
of of what makes us special relative to
kind of all the computation that's
happening in the universe. That's a bit
disappointing because it's not like
we're saying we're we're bigger and
better and we do more than what's
happening in the rest of the universe.
Actually quite the contrary, we're doing
something quite specific relative to
what happens in the rest of the
universe.
Well,
you kind of get some idea
uh if you think about the Ruliad, we
each mind is kind of uh
uh exists at some points in the Ruliad
and is kind of tracing some path through
the history of the Ruliad. And you can
kind of try and get some idea what's out
there in the space of possible minds.
Here's one very simple experiment you
can do. You could just say, let's take a
generative AI system and let's ask it to
make uh
uh
images and let's look at kind of the the
space of of possible images that it can
make, kind of its the expand its its
latent space.
What you can ask the question, well, if
you do that, uh you know, the the center
of this is a as a cat in a party hat,
but as you go out away from that, these
are things which that that that um are
kind of we can think of as a very very
tiny corner of the Ruliad that we're
exploring as we look at these different
pictures. So, one question you can ask
even for something like a a simple image
generation system is what fraction of
the images that the image generation
system can generate are actually things
that we humans, for example, have words
for or can be described. So, you know,
there may be 5,000 picturable nouns.
Those are in this whole space of
possible images, this little tiny corner
of the Ruliad that that corresponds to.
What What fraction of of those of that
um of those possible images are things
for which we have names?
The answer is unbelievably small. Even
in some very simple system, it might be
10 to the minus 500 of the of the
possible images of things for which we
as humans have currently come up with
words. So in a sense that's that's where
we've colonized in the ruliyad so to
speak are just those places where we
have uh particular words for things and
and a lot of what we see even in this
tiny corner that corresponds to
something that we've generated from from
uh a generative AI that we've trained on
on human images and so on. Even in uh
sort of that tiny corner we have things
for which we don't have words. Now, as
sort of uh
civilization progresses, maybe some of
these things will seem significant
enough that we will make up words for
them. Maybe our AIs will will show us
that this is a thing that's really a
useful kind of concept to have and we'll
introduce that. We'll add it to the
collection of words that we have in in
our language. I mean, I think brains of
our size probably do get to deal with
maybe 50,000 words. I don't think brains
of our size do very well with many more
than that. Um it's uh and you know, it's
an interesting question what kind of
structures beyond the kind of
compositional language that we have
someone get to go beyond kind of words
and the constructions we have of words.
Well,
so this this idea of kind of um
sort of what's out there in the space of
possible minds, what's out there in the
ruliyad, how do we perceive the ruliyad?
Uh one of the things that is notable is
when we have sort of nearby minds, they
perceive the ruliyad in in very much the
same way. It's kind of like being laid
out in physical space. Because we're all
on this one planet in this one galaxy,
we observe the universe in a particular
way and we all kind of agree about
roughly which stars are in the night sky
and so on.
But if we were and that's a consequence
of the fact that we're all pretty nearby
in physical space.
Well, it's the same thing in the Ruliad.
We're all in a sense minds, human minds,
are all pretty nearby in the kind of
space of possible minds in the Ruliad.
And I think that's sort of why we get to
believe in objective reality. It's
because we can kind of because our sort
of we're we're all sort of close
together in in the Ruliad, we all kind
of can we can we all sort of agree about
what is going on in the Ruliad. And we
can all kind of decide that yes, that's
really what's going on, that's objective
reality. So, one of the surprises about
that is to have this collection of
similar minds, we have to have things
that go rather beyond physics. To have a
collection of similar minds, you kind of
have to have biology. And so, then that
leads one to the question of okay, given
the Ruliad, what can we say about kind
of biology and life and so on? It's been
surprising to me that we end up being
able to say quite a few things about it.
Let me um
quickly talk about that. So, so this is
what we're thinking about and we're
going to come around to talking about
kind of what's what minds like ours are
like. And maybe I'll show you some
things that I just made this afternoon
that have something to say about that.
Um
so
this is kind of a very idealized version
of biology. So, over on the left is a
very simple genome. It's a cellular
automaton rule. Over on the right is
kind of what the developments of the
kind of idealized organism with that
genome will be like. And so, this
organism starts from that little seed.
It
it goes for a while, then it dies out.
Okay, so imagine that we're doing very
simple kind of biological evolution.
We're just mutating bits in the rule
that that determines the the the the
the genome for the system.
Well, we can we can keep doing that.
Every dot here corresponds to a possible
mutation. Most of the time we don't make
a better organism. A better in this case
is defined as living longer.
And but sometimes where there's a
breakthrough and we and we get to have a
a fitter organism. And we can see kind
of the sequence of kind of progressively
fitter organisms that we produce.
Well,
uh every time kind of we roll the dice,
we'll get a different sequence of
organisms. The thing that I find sort of
remarkable about this
is that the um uh the the the that kind
of
you kind of as as you develop through
kind of uh biological evolutionary time,
you're kind of coming up with different
ideas which you then build on to make
sort of a fitter and fitter organism.
And what we've realized recently, okay,
these are some pictures I just made a
few minutes ago. Um these are just
examples of uh kind of um
uh what happens when you uh run
different kinds of rules. Um these are
rules that have been evolved to live a
long time and then and then die out.
This is kind of some of what they do.
And there are lots of very surprising
things that happen. Uh one of the things
that's kind of notable, let's see what
else goes on here. I haven't looked at
all of these yet. Um
So, there are any more remarkable
creatures? Okay, there's this a pretty
surprising creature that just uh you
know, who would have imagined uh you
know, in the case of this creature, you
might say, "Well, you know, can you
explain the mechanism by which this
creature operates?"
Well, maybe a little bit with this one.
Probably not with one like this. You
just have to say, "Well, it lives for a
lot of steps and then it dies out."
Um
And uh
uh
but in any case, the the thing I think
this is actually a pretty good model for
a lot of things that emerge. That's one
I showed earlier. Um that uh that um
uh emerge in in biology. Um and it's
kind of a uh uh
Well, there's there's lots to say about
that. But in any case, the the um um
uh, the the main point is that
what we're getting in biology is the
sort of big stack of of discoveries. I
don't know whether the stack of
discoveries made in the history of of
3.5 billion years of biological history
is larger than or smaller than the stack
of discoveries that makes modern
technology. I'm guessing biology is
still ahead, but probably not by very
much. Um, but in any case, the the uh,
the thing that we see is that sort of
biology is using computational
irreducibility. It's kind of finding
ways to take sort of lumps of
computational irreducibility and stick
them together in ways that achieve the
purposes it wants to achieve of being a
fitter organism.
Well, turns out machine learning is
doing very much the same thing. So, you
take, you know, your your typical uh,
uh, your typical neural net um
and uh, you can it's kind of hard to
tell what neural nets are doing, but you
can kind of simplify them, just make
sort of a grid of of uh, of neurons.
And uh, you can simplify them even
further and just make a completely
discrete uh, kind of system that seems
to behave uh, much like a neural net. In
fact, probably if the technology was
built out, you'd be able to make sort of
completely discrete AI systems. Um,
this is a this is an example of uh, sort
of the uh, progressive evolution of the
pattern of weights effectively in this
completely discrete system.
What's notable is if you ask, if you run
the system a bunch of times and you say,
"Learn to in this case, I think it was
just live for 30 steps and then die out
for any initial pattern." Then
the uh, uh, the way that it does that is
is complicated. It's it's like what we
see in biology. It's kind of harnessing
computational irreducibility to do the
thing it wants to do.
And my guess is that that's a of
of kind of how brains work is that
inside there's sort of lumps of
computational irreducibility being put
together to achieve the purposes we want
to achieve. And the reason that work it
works is that the purposes we want to
achieve are computationally quite
simple. In other words, we're trying to
train a neural net to you know,
recognize cats from dogs. The ultimate
computational abilities of the neural
nets of the underlying computational
system in the neural net are vastly
greater than that. We're simply giving
it some very coarse thing that we want
it to do. And that very coarse thing we
can find ways to do by finding sort of
lumps of computational irreducibility
that can fit together to achieve that. I
kind of view machine learning as being
like if you want to build a wall, you
can do it not by making a series of kind
of very precisely defined bricks, but
instead by just picking up randomly
shaped rocks from the ground and trying
to fit them together to make a stone
wall.
So,
it's kind of that that's kind of the
picture that that the way that minds
work like ours is by this process of
sort of fitting together these lumps of
computational irreducibility.
So, one question you can ask is one sort
of old question in uh I suppose in
philosophy this sort of a philosophy
experiment this is a this afternoon's
results um has to do with if you are
kind of uh training let's say a neural
net
to
>> [clears throat]
>> do some to compute some particular
function let's say, what are all the
different ways that it can compute that?
Kind of like asking if you were a human
and you learn the color red, do we all
think about the color red in the same
way? Do we all have the same sort of
inner experience of the color red? Well,
you can do kind of a a piece of
experimental philosophy so to speak in a
modern sense to answer that question
with a neural net.
So, here what we've been doing is to
just say this is uh lots of different
training runs effectively for a
particular neural net learning to
reproduce this rather boring function
here. And as the loss goes down, as it
gets better at reproducing it, things go
more purple. And so here is
what you can see is there are many
different paths that all lead to sort of
the success in reproducing this function
that all kind of learn the color red,
but they do it in different ways. And so
you can kind of look at kind of the the
the patterns of sort of different ways
you can learn the same thing. And so
here are a few examples. Let's see, I
think I might have a nice example here.
These are examples of different
activation functions and so on and
different structures of the networks.
Some of what you see here is just a
consequence of simple permutation
symmetries and so on inside the network,
but some of what you see is kind of how
how how complicated is the pattern of
ways in which you can understand that
same concept.
So okay. Well, I think I'm about to run
out of time, so I should probably
um
What what does all of this kind of
computational thinking about things
where does it take us with respect to
minds, AIs, consciousness, and so on?
I mean, I think there's a sort of a
question
of
when we build
artificial minds, we build AIs, things
like that, we are building them in a way
that is still very close to us in the
Ruliad. Their minds are very very close
in Rulial space to us.
As we start exploring the Ruliad more
broadly, we are effectively creating
more and more alien minds.
In things in the computational
experiments I've done for years, one's
effectively going out and sort of going
to to create sort of explore artificial
universes, artificial minds, and one's
just jumping anywhere in the Ruliad.
The the challenge of jumping anywhere in
the Ruliad is what you get to is not
very human. It's not It's You don't get
to kind of
take what we humans sort of understand
and appreciate and and sort of map that
into what you observe when you jump to
some sort of random place in the rule
yard. And the way I see sort of the
progress of knowledge is as a
progressive sort of expansion of our
domain in the rule yard. Just as we send
out to the spacecraft to expand our
domain in physical space, so we're sort
of inventing new paradigms for thinking
about things, and that's kind of
expanding our domain in in rule yard
space.
And so, as we build out sort of more and
more sophisticated AIs, so to speak, we
can think of them potentially as
exploring more and more of rule yard
space.
Well, you might say that's that's great
and that's going to be very impressive
and so on. But the thing to realize is
most of the computation that goes on in
the rule yard is computation that is
very non-human and is sort of irrelevant
to us. So, we build our AIs, we try and
build these more and more sophisticated
computational systems, we end up with
things which are much more like nature
than they are like minds that we
recognize. It's like computations that
are just running, but the computations
are very non-human. They're computations
that are sort of out there in the rule
yard, but not computations that we that
are aligned with with the way that we
humans are. I think it's worth
understanding, you know, when people
sort of wonder what will it be like if
already is the case that there are sort
of more AIs running than there are human
minds, but what will it be sort of like
when much of the world is is kind of
operating in this kind of computational
structure of this kind of AI
civilization that is
that is something that we humans
can't really understand the details of,
just as we can't understand any of these
computationally irreducible processes,
we can't understand many of the kinds of
things that happen in nature.
Well, we can do our best to find kind of
try and find scientific laws, natural
laws, that allow us to make this bridge
between sort of what actually happens in
these possible minds and what we can
understand with human minds. But, it's
worth sort of understanding that a lot
of the things that happen in those
possible minds are things that we humans
just don't care about. They're things,
you know, as human civilization
progresses, the set of things that we
care about evolves quite slowly, and
it's kind of something where we there's
a continuity of kind of the things that
we care about over time. And that
continuity, as we as we think about sort
of the the continuation of that, we can
kind of see where that will go. But, we
actually we don't know where that will
go, but we can see that's a a sort of a
small path through the set of all
possible minds. Anyway, I that was a
very quick
trip through a few kinds of ideas that
perhaps might have some relevance to the
types of things that you guys are
interested in. And I hope we have time
for at least microscopic amount of time
for questions and comments and so on.
>> We do, definitely.
Um, but thank you so much, Stephen,
firstly.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you so much for being here with us
today, virtually. Um, I have so many
questions, but uh I'm only
pointing at at a couple things. Like, at
which level in the woollyad or in the
computations do we see the first put
whole structures emerge? Or in the
automata space as well. Another one is
related to um
when you say the mind is a multiway
system, very similar to the branching
universe, the brain, of course, is not
very good at handling that many
superpositions. So, it's going to yield
with a very finite sub spread resolution
that the brain is supporting for these
branches. Uh how many branches do you
actually have sometimes and how deep do
they go before they die out? And another
question is very tiny and technical and
it's when you define your world and the
being you say that you just need
relationships and identities. What do
you need identities for why can the
locations these atoms of space
not just be defined by the relations?
>> Okay, I'll take those last first.
So, the eons, the ultimate atoms of
existence.
What is important about those atoms of
existence is that they are distinct.
That's it.
They're distinct and they have relations
to other atoms of space.
Or atoms of existence.
There is no place that they are.
The place is defined by relations
between to other atoms of existence.
There is no sense in which you are
placing these atoms of existence because
there is no space.
It is the relations between these atoms
of existence that make space.
So, the thing that's important to
understand about them is is that they
have an identity. They are distinct. And
you can say you can say it's this atom
of existence that's related to this
other atom of existence.
Let's see. So, that that is that's that
one. The with respect to
multiway systems and brains, no, I think
the whole point is that it's sort of a
critical feature of of consciousness as
we experience it that we have one basic
thread of experience. We crush down
everything to one basic thread of
experience. What is
what what happens is is something like
the following. When we look at a fluid,
we perceive only the overall velocity
field of a bunch of molecules. We
perceive only the average of many
molecules. That's because we're pretty
big compared to those molecules. We're
we're aggregating the effect of many
molecules. So, I think what happens in
these multiway graphs is that our brains
in effect the
span this this region of branchial space
that is large compared to the individual
threads of history. And so we're doing
that same kind of averaging of the
threads of history that happens when we
make averages of individual molecules in
a in in space. And so what's what's
what's then happening is yes, we are
crushing everything down to a single
experience, a single thread of
experience. And there's a lot of detail
about sort of what happens when you
insist that things be consistent. You we
say it's all crushed down to this one
thread of experience. Well, that might
not be consistent. It's just like we
might say we're describing a fluid just
in terms of a velocity field, but that
might not be enough. Somewhere inside
the thing that's making up that velocity
field, the molecules might all gang up
together and make themselves do
something which cannot be described by
simple velocity field. But it's kind of
the the scientific result is that that
doesn't happen. It's sort of a
consequence of computational
irreducibility that that doesn't happen.
And I think it's the same thing with
these threads of history that at least
locally we can conflate together those
different threads of history. If our
minds were spread too widely in
branchial space, we wouldn't be able to
do that. Just like if if we were sort of
spread too wide in in physical space, we
would conclude very different things
about how physical space works.
And the other thing you asked was about
control structures. I don't know exactly
what that means. Um the you know, if you
ask about sort of any computational
phenomenon, then
you can ask can you achieve that
computational phenomenon in a system
like this? And the answer is always yes.
And there's a question, how difficult is
it to achieve that? That's an
interesting question, actually. I
studied that recently. Um the question
is kind of if you're undergoing adaptive
evolution, for example, how hard is it
to get to a certain kind of outcome? And
you can kind of define the mutational
complexity of things, which is sort of
how hard is it to reach that thing by
doing it adaptive evolution.
Um and that's uh and I think one of the
one of the big conclusions there, okay,
is relevant to biology and probably a
bunch of other things, is that if you
have a system which is adaptively
evolved to achieve a simple-to-describe
purpose,
then that fact alone, independent of
kind of what that purpose is, has
implications for the structure of the
system and seems to imply that there
will be sort of certain elements of
apparent mechanism in the behavior of
the system, even though the overall
behavior of the system will be
computationally reducible. I'm I'm I'm
skipping, you know, the equivalent of
thousands of pages of detail here, but
that's a that's an attempt to kind of
um address a couple of those those
questions. And I think, you know, one of
the things that is
a a challenge right now, and an
interesting one, is is the existence of
observers like us,
and many of them, inevitable in the
ruleiad? And I think the answer will be
yes,
but that's something that we can
scientifically address. And we can
address, you know, given that, we can
also say, well, there'll be a bunch of
other observers, too, that correspond to
kind of alien minds. And we can ask,
well, how far away in ruleal space are
those alien minds? What is the
possibility that we could communicate
with those alien minds? You know, forget
the sort of the light-years of physical
space separating us from, you know,
other stars or whatever else.
When we are dealing with sort of alien
minds that we might say, well, they
follow the same
what what, you know, how far away are
they? What's the distribution of alien
minds in the universe or in the ruleiad?
So, these are things where I think there
is my my feeling is that that one of the
big things that we're we're going to
discover is that just as the the core
laws of physics
are consequences of the fact that we are
observers of the kind we are. My guess
is that many details of the universe as
we perceive it are also consequences of
the fact that we are contingently, so to
speak, observers of the way we are. So,
for example, one of the one of the
things I realized recently is sort of
obvious at some level is the fact that
we perceive the universe the way we do
is a consequence of the fact that we
have non-zero mass. It's not obvious
that we would have non-zero mass. We
could have been made of purely made of
photons. If we were purely made of
photons, we simply wouldn't perceive we
we we would not perceive time. Um we
would
uh and things would be very different.
The fact that we have mass is a an
important part of the way that we
perceive the universe.
The thing I'm really chasing is why do
we perceive the universe to have three
dimensions of space
or at least in our models roughly three
dimensions of space.
My guess is that in the end that will be
a painfully obvious feature of the way
we are as observers. I mean, we can we
can start listing ways in which we're
sort of things we assume about
ourselves. So, for example, another
critical assumption in science is that
we have the free will to do any
experiment we want.
In other words, it's not the case that
every experiment we do is kind of
pre-wired. We imagine that we can sort
of poke the universe and kind of sample
different things and then use some kind
of scientific induction to deduce what's
going on as opposed to the idea that
we're sort of constantly puppeted to do
just the particular experiment we do.
So, there's a there's a long list of
these kinds of things. But I I think
sort of the the thing that's perhaps
interesting from a sort of an arc of the
of the story of science is that what is
becoming clear is that to understand
more about the foundations of science,
we have to understand more about
ourselves and the way that that sort of
the the the the the way that we perceive
the universe is inevitably a consequence
of the way that we are. It's not
something where we can say the universe
fundamentally is this way. The only
thing we can say is fundamentally
there's the ruliad, but then the
question of how we perceive it and what
slice of it we're in is something that
depends on kind of our nature as a as
observers.
I I I I we should say that I think
this kind of whole
effort of kind of doing um
um
uh we have somebody with a microphone.
All right. Let's let's
uh please
>> Is this on?
>> Yeah.
>> Hey, this is Gil Verdun. Nice to see you
again from Extropic.
So,
you applied the um
the ruliad and and the multiway graph to
explaining quantum mechanics, uh but as
we know the brain is a a stochastic
thermodynamic system. It's it's not
necessarily
the quantum mechanics gets kind of
averaged out. Uh it's a mesoscale
system. Have you thought about uh
connecting your theory to stochastic
thermodynamics or out-of-equilibrium
thermodynamics could because it it seems
like a a stochastic path integral to me.
And then there could be some interesting
connections to Friston's work on uh the
generalized free energy principle and
the maximum caliber principle there and
and some formal connections to to
Bayesian inference potentially, uh but I
don't know if you thought about
exploring
machine learning through that that that
that path. Yeah.
>> Not as deeply as I think you've thought
about it.
>> [laughter]
>> Um
the uh
I think um
uh so I shouldn't you know, the whole
question about quantum mechanics and
brains, I don't think quantum mechanics
is relevant to most of what happens in
brains. If we imagine that it was,
uh you know, if you and that there was
something sort of very magic about
brains that needed sort of new physics
that was different from the everyday,
I think that the success of LLMs is kind
of the last nail in that coffin.
>> Right.
>> You know, it doesn't the the brain
doesn't need anything special in terms
of physics. Now, the question of of what
uh you know,
studying the kinds of systems I've
looked at and and uh looking at kind of
stochasticity, I'm never a big believer
in fundamental stochasticity because I
think when you're looking at fundamental
science, not technology, that's a quite
different story, kind of to say that
something is stochastic is to say, "Oh,
there's something happening in the
system that I don't have a model for.
I'm just going to say that it's random."
So, in a lot of systems, one of the big
sort of discoveries is that sort of
randomness
very close to, you know, very good
randomness is very easy to get.
And so, when you're looking at
thermodynamic systems and so on, I mean,
the the you know, my sort of derivation
of the second law of thermodynamics
relies on the idea that everything is
completely deterministic. But, the the
to the observer like us who is
computationally bounded, it is something
that appears stochastic because we can't
untangle it to say, "No, no, no, we know
what the underlying rule is."
Now, to the question of of what um
um
uh kind of how observers like us
perceive that and and what you know,
what aspects of that underlying system
we can perceive, I think this is I think
is what Carl Preston uh likes to think
about and so on. Um I'm not sure that I
have and maybe he has better
characterizations of sort of what all
the possible things that minds like ours
can perceive from from these underlying
systems uh uh uh are like. But, uh and I
don't know.
Okay, so so I've studied a bit
um
things like when you have these kinds of
systems that we're looking at,
things about um
uh
oh
things like what
what effects do perturbations have? So,
I'll show you one thing maybe um see
>> Can I ask you a related question to what
you just said?
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> So, I agree with almost everything you
said about the rulead. By the way,
Andrew Critch, nice to meet you.
Um
also agree that thermodynamics, you
know, the second law being entailed from
being computationally bounded and having
single-threaded memory, but I don't
agree with you that relativity and
quantum mechanics are entailed by those
properties of us as observers. So, my
two questions for you are number one, is
there not part of the rulead with minds
very similar to ours running on
Newtonian mechanics on a flat space-time
and no quantum?
Uh and if yes, my second question is how
then do our observer properties entail
quantum and relativity as distinct from
Newtonian mechanics?
>> Right. So, it is completely not obvious
that uh you know, computa- computational
irreducibility plus observers like us
plus you know, represented in terms of
hypergraphs and hypergraph rewriting
implies relativity and quantum
mechanics. It's completely not obvious.
Okay? It's I mean, in fact, one of my
big efforts right now is to kind of
build a more and more rigorous stack to
be able to make that argument. I mean,
we can make that argument at So, in the
typical uh
way that sort of a lot of science
progresses, you know, there's a
physicist way of making an argument and
then there's the pure mathematician's
way of making the argument. We are, I
would say, roughly at the physicist
level of making the argument and not at
the pure mathematician level of making
the argument. Now, to make one feel
better about that, the derivation of
fluid mechanics from molecular dynamics
has never been got to the pure
mathematician level. That's always been
an argument that is uh
in fact, the things I've I've tried to
do um are the closest we're getting to
having a really rigorous argument for
why the the second law of thermodynamics
works and so on, why you can get fluid
mechanics from discrete microdynamics.
So, now the question of how do you get
relativity and so on from discrete
hypergraph rewriting, all that kind of
thing, um, it's I mean, it's a tolerably
simple argument that I could give you in
maybe 10 minutes with a bit of vagueness
about how that works, kind of an
intuitive argument for why that works.
Um, to give something more rigorous,
there's kind of a we already know the
the 10-hour version of that. We are
working on the the multi-month version
of that, which really involves building
what we call infra-geometry. So, basic
point is
in
traditional differential geometry, for
example, on which things like general
relativity are built, one starts from a
manifold where little tiny patches of
the manifold look just like Euclidean
space.
And the, um, uh, what we have is
something where little tiny patches of
space look like these of hypergraph. And
so, you have to end up building this
this basically, actually it's kind of
fun. I've been going back to literally
what Euclid said. Uh, he starts with his
first his first, uh, kind of, uh,
statement is a point is that which has
no part,
which for us isn't even true.
So, we have to kind of recapitulate
Euclid and build this whole stack of
mathematics to get to the point where we
can make a rigorous argument for what's
going on. Can you could you make
Newtonian mechanics in a way that that,
uh, uh,
uh, fits into these the the system we're
building? No, you cannot. It just won't
work. It's it's, um, what ends up
happening is the causal relations
between, uh, rewriting events, uh,
essentially define, uh, a sort of a
graph of causality. And that graph of
causality is it is inevitable that you
have to get relativistic mechanics, not
Newtonian mechanics from that. Again,
not This is not obvious. This not It's
not I I I can't Just by saying it, I'm
not making the argument, so to speak.
But,
I think that is something that will
probably have an increasingly rigorous
way of of showing that that's the way
things work.
>> Well, thank you so much, Stephen, for
joining us virtually. Thank you so much
for your talk and for the questions.
[applause]
>> Nice to see you.